[MUSIC]
[음악]
Okay, so we've talked about how to represent documents and
문서 표현하는 법과
we've also talked about how to measure similarity between documents.
문서 간 유사도를 측정하는 법을 알아봤습니다
So now let's turn to the actual task of interest which is retrieving a document.
이제 실제 관심사인 문서 검색으로 들어가 봅시다
So someone is reading an article, we're assuming they like that article and
누군가 기사를 읽는데 그 기사를 좋아해서
we'd like to present them with another article to read.
다른 기사도 보여주려 한다고 합시다
So in particular one of the most popular ways of doing this something called
가장 인기 있는 방법은
nearest neighbor search, where we have our query article.
최근접 이웃 검색이란 겁니다 검색 기사가 있을 때
That's the article that were reading.
지금 읽고 있는 기사죠
And then there's the corpus.
말뭉치도 있습니다
That's all of the documents out there that we want to search over to
검색을 전개하고자 하는 모든 문서의 총합이고
recommend some new article.
여기서 추천할 새 기사를 고르게 되죠
And so what we need to do for
최근접 이웃 검색을 위해서는
our nearest neighbor search is we need to specify a distance metric.
거리 기준을 확립해야 합니다
So this is gonna be our measure of similarity that we talked
이전에 논한 유사도 측정이
about earlier and
될 테고
then what this algorithm is gonna output is a collection of related articles.
알고리즘은 관련 기사 모음을 결과물로 내놓습니다
So one example of nearest neighbor search is something called one nearest neighbor,
최근접 이웃 검색의 예 하나는 1-최근접 이웃인데
where you have your query article and what you're gonna return is just simply
검색 기사에서 모든 기사 중
the most related article, out of all those articles out there, to the query article.
가장 관련된 기사를 반환합니다
And the algorithm is very straightforward.
알고리즘은 아주 간단합니다
We're just gonna search over every article in our corpus,
말뭉치의 모든 기사에서 검색해서
these are all these little green articles, and we're gonna compute the similarity
초록색 기사들인데 아까 설명드린 방법으로
using the methods that we described earlier between the query article and
검색 기사와 말뭉치 기사 간의
this article we're examining in the corpus.
유사도를 계산합니다
And then,
그리고
if that similarity is better than the best similarity that we've found so far,
유사도가 지금까지의 최고 유사도보다 높다면
then we're gonna keep this article as our best article that we've found so far.
이 기사를 다시 선택합니다
And then at the end after we've iterated through every article in our corpus
말뭉치의 모든 기사를 훑은 다음에
we're gonna look at what was the best article that we found.
가장 유사도가 높은 기사를 살펴봅니다
And we're gonna recommend this to the reader.
그리고 이걸 사용자에게 추천하죠
A very straightforward variant of this is something called k- nearest neighbor
이 알고리즘의 간단한 변형은 k-최근접 이웃 검색인데
search, where instead of just outputting the most relevant article that we've
가장 관련 있는 기사를 출력하는 대신
found, we're gonna present the reader with a collection of k different articles
가장 관련 있는 k개의 기사 모음을
that are the top k most relevant articles.
보여줍니다
And the way that we do this,
그러기 위해
the algorithm is newly identical except in instead of keeping just the most related
알고리즘은 가장 관련 있는 하나만 저장하는 건 동일하지만
article, we're gonna keep a priority queue of the top k articles found so far.
우선순위 큐로 기사 k개를 유지한다는 게 다릅니다